Guide to the Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia records, 1951-1994 MS2078
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia records
1951-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2078
1 Linear Feet
Records consist of newsletters, meeting minutes, correspondence, member directories, program booklets, field trip records, maps, news clippings, and announcements of organizational events. One folder contains miscellaneous materials, mostly newsletters from other Civil War Round Tables across the countryfrom the Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia cover the years 1951 to 1994. The bulk of the contents can be found from 1951 to 1959.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition data is unknown
Historical or Biographical Note
The original Civil War Round Table was founded in 1935 by four men who had an interest in the Civil War and wanted to interest others as well. The four founding members were Joseph Mills Hanson, Garret Jex, James Turner, and William Webb. In 1952 the Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia on which this collection is based was founded.
The Round Table was actively involved in the preservation of Civil War and Civil War era historical sites in the Washington DC area. The Round Table was influential in the establishment of the National Civil War Centennial Commission. Every fall and spring field trips were organized to Civil War battlefields and were led by members of the Round Table who had distinguished themselves as experts in a certain topic of the Civil War or by other local Civil War specialists. At the Round Table's annual dinners, known as Gold Medal Award Ceremonies, the Gold Medal of the Civil War Round Table was awarded to persons who had made outstanding achievements in the field of Civil War history. The Constitution and By-Laws of the Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia were revised and updated on September 18, 1951 and again on February 20, 1962.
The Round Table held meetings every second Tuesday of the month, September through June. Originally meetings were held in the homes of the members, but as membership increased meetings were moved to the Army and Navy Club in Washington D.C. During the years 1961 to 1965, the Centennial of the Civil War, membership rose to over five hundred members. This increase in membership moved the meetings to the Ballroom of the National Press Club in Washington D.C. Meetings were later moved to the Fort Lesley J. McNair Officer's Club in Washington D.C., the final meeting place of the Round Table, as far as the collection shows. After the increase in membership during the Centennial, membership dropped sharply but has recently begun to increase.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection of records from the Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia cover the years 1951 to 1994. These records are contained in two boxes in the Special Collections Department of the George Washington University library. The boxes hold a number of folders, arranged in chronological order. The collection consists of newsletters, meeting minutes, correspondence, member directories, program booklets, field trip records, maps, news clippings, and announcements of organizational events. One folder contains miscellaneous materials, mostly newsletters from other Civil War Round Tables across the country. The bulk of the contents can be found from 1951 to 1959.
Newsletters make up the bulk of the contents starting in 1968. Occasionally the folders will contain large numbers of meeting minutes. Also beginning around 1968, most of the folders contain nearly complete runs of newsletters; the closer the dates approach to the present, the more complete the newsletters become.
Several copies and revisions of the Round Table's Constitution and By-Laws exist among the contents of the collection, as well as numerous program booklets from Gold Medal Award Dinners held by the Round Table.
Overall, the contents of this collection are in good condition. The majority of the newsletters are intact and have not been subjected to severe wear and tear. The staples have not rusted too much nor contaminated the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
By-laws; Military maps; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Washington (D.C.); Maps; Webb, William; Jex, Garnet W.; Turner, James; Hanson, Joseph Mills; Civil War Round Table of the District of Columbia
- Records, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  [From original finding aid] 1. News clipping Undated 2. History and Activities Sheet 3. Constitution and By-Laws- Revised 09/18/1951 4. Meeting Minutes 09/18/1951 5. Newsletters 01/1951, 1:2 08/29/1951
- Records, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  [From original finding aid] 1. Correspondence 09/05/1952 11/21/1952 2. Events Announcements 01/01/1952 01/01/1952; 09/16/1952; 11/18/1952; 3. Notes- "First Round Table Debate" 12/03/1952 4. Field Trip Records 06/1952- "Battlefield Expedition" 06/19/1952-06/23/1952 5. Bulletins 06/10/1952-08/07/1952 6. Meeting Minutes 05/20/1952 7. Newsletters 01/07/1952, 2:7 01/1952 03/1952, 2:1 04/1952, 2:2 05/1952, 2:3 10/01/1952, 2:4 12/05/1952, 2:6
- Records, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events Announcements 01/05/1953-01/03/1953 Unspecified year Unspecified year 2. Newsletters 01/04/1953, 3:1 03/05/1953, 3:2 04/15/1953, 3:3 05/15/1953, 3:4 08/17/1953, 3:510/06/1953, 3:6 10/28/1953, 3:7 12/03/1953, 3:8
- Records, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  [From original finding aid] 1.History and Activities Sheet 2. Undated proposed Constitution and By-Laws 3. Undated list of officers, committee members, and membership directory 4. Newsletters 01/08/1954, 3:9 01/05/1954, 4:1 03/05/1954, 4:2 04/10/1954, 4:3 05/04/1954, 4:4 08/21/1954, 4:5 09/25/1954, 4:6 10/11/1954, 4:7 11/03/1954, 4:8 11/24/1954, 4:9 12/23/1954, 4:10 Undated Undated 5. Miscellaneous undated letterhead
- Records, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Correspondence 01/25/1955 2. Program booklet, "Third Gold Medal Award Ceremony"- 04/12/1955 3. Newsletters 01/25/1955, 5:1 01/28/1955, 5:2 03/25/1955, 5:3 04/29/1955, 5:4 05/31/1955, 5:508/05/1955, 5:609/01/1955, 5:710/01/1955, 5:8 11/01/1955, 5:9 12/01/1955, 5:10
- Records, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events announcements 05/01/1956 09/04/195610/01/1956 11/1956 12/1956 2. Program booklet, "Fourth Gold Medal Award Ceremony"- 04/10/1956 3. Events booklet- 1955-1956 4. Tour booklet- 05/19/1956 5. Newsletters 01/01/1956, 6:1 01/01/1956, 6:2 03/01/1956, 6:304/01/1956, 6:4 05/01/1956, 6:5 06/01/1956, 6:6 08/25/1956, 6:710/01/1956, 6:8 11/01/1956, 6:9 12/01/1956, 6:10
- Records, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Questionnaire 1957 2. Events Booklet- 1956 -1957 3. Events Announcements 01/1957; 01/1957; 03/1957; 05/1957; 09/10/1957; 10/07/1957; 11/1957; 12/1957 4. Newsletters 06/1957; 09/1957; 12/1957 vo 7, no 1-10
- Records, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Field trip record- 09/20/1958 2. Events Booklet- 1957 -1958 3. Events Announcements 01/1958; 01/1958; 03/1958 05/1958 10/ 1958; 11/1958; 12/1958 4. Newsletters -6/1958; 09/1958; 12/1958 vo 8, no 1-10
- Records, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events Booklet- 1958-1959 2. Program Booklet, "Centennial Night Program"- 11/10/1959 3. News clipping 11/06/1959 4. Events Announcements 01/1959; 01/1959; 05/1959; 09/1959; 10/1959; 11/1959; 12/1959 5. Newsletters 04/1959; 07/1959; 09/1959; 12/1959, vo 9, no 1-9
- Records, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events Booklet- 1959 -1960 2. Events Announcements 01/1960 01/1960; 03/1960; 05/1960
- Records, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events Announcement 01/1961 2. Newsletter 05/1961, 10:10 3. Field trip record 05/20/1961
- Records, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Constitution and By-Laws- 01/20/1962 2. Events/Program Booklet, "Gold Medal Program and Yearbook"- 1961-1962 3. Events Announcement 04/17/1962 4. Correspondence 11/14/1962 5. Newsletters 01/1962, 11:6 03/1962, 11:7 05/1962, 11:8 09/1962, 12:1
- Records, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events/Program Booklet, "Gold Medal Program and Yearbook"- 1962-1963 2. Seating List, "Gold Medal Dinner"- 04/16/1963 2 copies, different formats 3. Field Trip Record- 05/18/1963
- Records, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  [From original finding aid] 1.History and Activity Sheet- Revised copy, 1964 2. Correspondence 06/12/1964 06/18/1964 3. Notes Panel discussion- 03/17/1964 4. Guest List, "Twelfth Annual Gold Medal Dinner"- 04/21/1964 5. Events/Program Booklet, "Gold Medal Program and Yearbook"- 1963-1964 6. Newsletter 11/1964, vo 14, no 3
- Records, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Officer and Executive Directory- 1964-1965 2. Events/Program Booklet, "Gold Medal Program and Yearbook"- 1964-1965 3. Gold Medal order form and Inscription instructions - 04/13/1965 (3 sheets total) 4. Correspondence/ Memos 01/28/1965; 01/04/1965; 01/05/1965; 03/11/1965; 03/12/1965; 05/07/1965; 06/24/1965; 07/25/1965; 07/25/1965; 07/30/1965 5. Meeting Minutes- 06/21/1965 6. Treasurer's report - 06/21/1965 7. Events Announcement 04/13/1965 8. Field trip records Undated Undated, "16' Annual Battlefield Tour"
- Records, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Program Booklet, "Gold Medal Award Program"- 1966 2. Correspondence 01/16/1966; 01/1966; 04/16/1966 3. Miscellaneous Undated officer list
- Records, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Field trip record 09/30/1967 2. Program Booklet, "Gold Medal Award Program"- 1967 3. Newsletter 12/1967, 17:4
- Records, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  1.Meeting Minutes 01/01/1968; 05/01/1968; 09/05/1968 2. Notes 05/08/1968 3. Correspondence 05/08/1968 4. Events announcement 01/06/1968
- Records, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  [From original finding aid] 1.House of Representatives Bill 03/03/1969 04/16/1969 2. News clipping 05/11/1969 3. Events announcements/Field Trip Record 10/18/1969 4. Correspondence 04/24/1969 5. Newsletters 04/ 1968, 18:4 10/ 1969, 19:2 11/1969 19:3
- Records, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Meeting minutes 08/12/1970 2. Newsletters 01/1970, Vol. 19, No. 4 01/1970, Vol. 19, No. 5 03/1970, Vol. 19 04/ 1970, Vol. 19, No. 8 05/1970, Vol. 19, No. 9 09/ 1970, Vol. 20, No. 1 10/ 1970, Vol. 20, No. 2 12/1970, Vol. 20, No. 4
- Records, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Officer list- 1970-1971 2. Newsletters 01/1971, Vol. 20, No. 5 03/1971, Vol. 20, No. 7 04/ 1971, Vol. 20, No. 8 05/1971, Vol. 20, No. 9 09/ 1971, Vol. 21, No. 1 10/ 1971, Vol. 21, No. 2 11/1971, Vol. 21, No. 3 12/1971, Vol. 21, No. 4
- Records, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Member directory- 1971-1972 2. Additions to Membership Directory- 1971-1972 3. Field Trip Record 10/14/1972 3a. Two maps, 10/14/1972 4. Newsletters 01/1972, Vol. 21, No. 5 01/1972, Vol. 21, No.6 04/ 1972, Vol. 21, No. 8 05/1972, Vol. 21, No. 9 09/ 1972, Vol. 22, No. 1 10/ 1972, Vol. 22, No. 2
- Records, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Member directory- 1972-1973 2. Additions to the directory- 1972-1973 3. Map 1973 4. Field trip record 05/12/1973 10/13/1973 (two different records) 5. Meeting Minutes 07/10/1973 6. Newsletters 01/1973, Vol. 22, No. 5 03/1973, Vol. 22, No. 7 04/ 1973, Vol. 22, No. 8 05/1973, Vol. 22, No. 9 09/ 1973, Vol. 23, No. 1 10/ 1973, Vol. 23, No. 2 11/1973, Vol. 23, No. 3 12/1973, Vol. 23, No.4
- Records, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Committee appointees- 08/14/1974 2. Additions to the directory- 01/04/1974 3. Newsletters 01/1974, Vol. 23, No. 5 01/1974, Vol. 23, No. 6 03/1974, Vol. 23, No. 7 04/ 1974, Vol. 23, No. 8 05/1974, Vol. 23, No. 9 06/1974, Vol. 23, No. 10 09/ 1974, Vol. 24, No. 1 10/ 1974, Vol. 24, No. 2 Special Edition 1974 11/1974, Vol. 24, No. 3 12/1974, Vol. 24, No. 4
- Records, 1951-1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Field trip record 10/18/1975 2. List of Civil War Round Table presidents- 1951-1975 2 copies 3. Newsletters 01/1975, Vol. 24, No. 5 01/1975, Vol. 24, No. 6 03/1975, Vol. 24, No. 7 04/ 1975, Vol. 24, No. 8 05/1975, Vol. 24, No. 9 06/1975, Vol. 24, No. 10 09/ 1975, Vol. 25, No. 1 10/ 1975, Vol. 25, No. 2 11/1975, Vol. 25, No. 3 12/1975, Vol. 25, No. 4
- Records, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Meeting Minutes 06/24/1976 2. Memos 1976 06/11/1976 08/16/1976 09/20/1976 3. Newsletters 01/1976, Vol. 25, No. 5 01/1976, Vol. 25, No. 6 03/1976, Vol. 25, No. 7 04/ 1976, Vol. 25, No. 8 05/1976, Vol. 25, No. 9 06/1976, Vol. 25, No. 10 09/ 1976, Vol. 26, No. 1 10/ 1976, Vol. 26, No. 2 11/1976, Vol. 26, No. 3 12/1976, Vol. 26, No. 4
- Records, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Report, AD Hoc Award Committee- 1976-1977 2. Memos 01/28/1977; 01/24/1977;06/22/1977 3. Correspondence 05/21/1977; 05/22/1977; 06/15/1977 4. Extract from Civil War Round Table Digest Vol 8 No 4- 04/1977 5. Meting Minutes 01/22/1977; 07/14/1977 6. Field trip record- 10/22/1975 7. Newsletters 01/1977, Vol. 26, No. 5 01/1977, Vol. 26, No. 6 03/1977, Vol. 26, No. 7 04/ 1977, Vol. 26, No. 8 05/1977, Vol. 26, No. 9 06/1977, Vol. 26, No. 10 09/ 1977, Vol. 27, No. 1 10/ 1977, Vol. 27, No. 2 11/1977, Vol. 27, No. 3 12/1977, Vol. 27, No. 4
- Records, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Memo 06/21/1978 2. Notes, "Possible contribution to Battlefield Preservation Fund"- 1978 3. Field Trip Record 10/14/1978 4. Newsletters January- 06/1978, vol 27, no 5-10; 09/- 12/1978, vol 28, no 1-4
- Records, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Correspondence 01/20/1979 06/12/1979; 06/29/1979; 06/29/1979- attached to 06/25/1979; 06/05/1979; 04/07/1978; 04/05/1978; 10/25/1979; 11/23/1979 2. Newsletters January- 06/1979, vol 28, no 5-1; 09/1979-12/1979, vol 29, no 1-4 3. Field trip record 05/12/1979 (attached to 05/`79 newsletter)%32882014873650
- Records, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory- 1979-1980 2. Meeting report- 01/09/1980 3. Meeting Minutes 07/30/1980 4. Events Announcement 09/18/1980 5. Newsletters 01/1980-05/1980, vol 29, no 5-9; 09/1979-12/1979, vol 30, no 1-4 6. Field Trip Record 05/17/1980 (attached to 05/`80 newsletter)%32882014873650
- Records, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Meeting Minutes 07/27/1981 2. Memo 06/15/1981 3. Newsletters January- 05/1981, vol 30, no 5-9; 09/- 12/1981, vol 31, no 1-4
- Records, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory- 1981-1982 2. Newsletters January- 05/1982, vol 31, no 5-9; 09/1982-11/1982, vol 32, no 1-3
- Records, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory- 1982-1983 2. Field Trip Record 11/05/1983 3. Meeting Minutes 07/11/1983 4. Memo 06/17/1983 5. Newsletters 01/1983-05/1983, vol 32, no 5-9; 09/1983-12/1983, vol 33, no 1-4
- Records, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Newsletters 01/1984-05/1984, vol 33, no 5-9; 09/1984-12/1984, vol 34, no 1-4
- Records, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Newsletters 01/1985, 34:6 03/1985, 34:7 04/ 1985, 34:8 05/1985, 34:9 09/ 1985, 35:1 10/1985, 35:2 12/1985, 35: 4
- Records, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory- 1985-1986 2. Newsletters 01/1986, 35:5 01/1986, 35:6 03/1986, 35:8 05/1986, 35:9 09/1986, 36:1 10/1986, 36:2 11/1986, 36:3 12/1986, 36:4
- Records, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Events Announcement 03/28/1987 2. Newsletters 01/1987, 36:5 01/1987, 36:6 03/1987, 36:7 04/1987, 36:8 05/1987, 36:9 09/1987, 37:1 11/1987, 37:3
- Records, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory of the "American Revolution Round Table of the district of Columbia"- 1988 2. Newsletters 01/1988, 37:6 03/1988, 37:7 05/1988, 37:9 10/ 1988, 38: 2 11/1988, 38:3 12/1988, 38:4
- Records, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory- 1988-1989 2. Report of the Treasurer in Chief- 1989 3. Guest List, "Eight Annual Civil War Round Table Conference"- 1989 4. Excerpt from Chi Dispatch January- 01/1989, pg 3-13 5. Newsletters 01/1989, 38:6 03/1989, 38:7 04/1989, 38:8 05/1989, 38: 9 09/1989, 39:1 11/1989, 39:3 12/1989, 39:4
- Records, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Speaker List- 1990-1991 2. Meeting Minutes 06/19/1990 3. Newsletters 01/1990, 39:5 01/1990, 39:6 03/1990, 39:7 04/1990, 39:8 05/1990, 39:9 11/1990, 40:3 12/1990, 40:4
- Records, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Correspondence 04/10/1991 2. Membership Directory- 1990-1991 3. Newsletters 01/1991, 40:6 03/1991, 40:7 04/1991, 40:8 05/1991, 40:9 09/1991, 41:1 10/1991, 41:2 12/1991, 41:4
- Records, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  [From original finding aid] 1. "Suggested List of Readings- Battle of Monocacy" 2. Newsletters 01/1992, 41:5 01/1992, 41:6 03/1992, 41:7 04/1992, 41:8 05/1992, 41:9 06/1992, 41:10 09/ 1992, 42:1 10/1992, 42:2 11/1992, 42:3 12/1992, 42:4
- Records, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Membership Directory- 1993 2. Packet, "Monocacy, Lew Wallace, and Jubal Early's Raid on Washington-The Confederate Quest for Fame"- 01/12/1993 3. Events Announcement 04/24/1993 4. Newsletters 01/1993, 42:5 01/1993, 42:6 05/1993, 42:9 09/1993, 43:1
- Records, 1994; 3 Linear Feet (Box 2, Folder 17)
  [From original finding aid] 1.Newsletters 01/1994, 43:6 12/1994, 44:4
- Records, 1972-1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  [From original finding aid]Miscellaneous 1. Newsletters "The Dispatch"- Civil War Round Table of New York, Inc.- 10/1985, 35:2 "The Dispatch"- Civil War Round Table of New York, Inc.- 11/1985, 35:3 "The Prison Civil War Round Table Newsletter"- 1977 The Civil War Round Table of Wilmington- 04/1988 The Civil War Round Table of Northern New Jersey 1979-1980 2. Field Trip Record "Florida's Decisive Civil War Battle of Olustee," undated 05/04/1972-05/07/1972- "22nd Annual Battlefield Tour" 04/30- 05/04/1975- "251 Battlefield Tour" 05/2-6, 1984- "34' Annual Battlefield Tour" 3. Battlefield Booklets Gettysburg Antietam 4. Map, undated 5. Program Booklet, "400th Meeting"- 04/10/1981 6. Civil War Round Table Roster- pg 5, undated 7. Bibliography, undated 8. Civil War Library List, undated 9. Records Speech/Report- "A Memorial to Longstreet is Long Overdue," undated Receipt- "The Career of Captain Grant Marsh " undated Book Offer Order Form, undated Sticker- "Joe Hooker's Pride," undated Unspecified List of Names and Addresses, undated Bell Atlantic Phone Plan- 01/1989